We have seen both while loops and for loops
in our coverage of loops.
While loops are used for conditional situations,
and for loops are run a set number of times.
You may sometimes want one loop inside another
when you have multiple loops to run.
Having one loop inside of another is known
as having a nested loop.
Here is a pseudo-gaming situation: a player
has three lives with a goal to get into 10
positions in each life.
The player can make these position goals as
long as the game progresses.
We want updates each time a player makes a
position.
To accomplish this goal, look at the following
code in the 226-nested file.
On line 1, we have a Boolean variable, game_state,
set to True when the game is being played.
On line 2, we have a game_lives variable set
to 1.
Lines 3 through 7 have a while statement with
both a loop and a decision flow.
The while statement is necessary because we
have a condition: run this code as long as
game_lives is less than 3.
The for loop runs through, 10 times, an indicator
of what positions the player reached and during
which life those positions were reached.
Following the for loop, a player moves on
to the next life so long as the game is still
playing, as indicated on lines 6 and 7.
This code could have many more logical situations,
like a game being paused, but this topic's
focus is nested loops, which is why I left
that logic out.
Finally, line 8 shows a thank you statement
as a print statement.
I will run this code.
The code works, but we could use two adjustments.
First, the positions should run 1 through
10, not 0 through 9.
Secondly, the code stops at the second life.
What two adjustments do you see to be made
to the code?
The first adjustment should be on line 3,
where we need to change the operator to less
than or equal so that the code loops through
this while statement on the third life.
Secondly, we need the range to go from 1 to
11, as, if you recall, a range with two numbers
starts on the first number and ends just before
the last number, this time just using the
numbers needed rather than a plus one, as
we did in a previous topic.
I will make that change to the range on line
4, rerun the code, and we see the 10 position
messages inside each life.
Knowing how to use nested loops allows one
to know when to run one process inside of
another, which is a common occurrence in programming
logic.